software engineering radio episode 55
refactoring pub tool
hello listeners thanks for joining
Software Engineering radio once again in
this episode ever hot and ma teen will
continue their discussion about
refactoring they're going to talk
specifically about large or bigger
refactorings in this episode sorry for
the somewhat not so great sound quality
we had to do some post-processing of the
recording because of noise that was on
the recording and you can hear some of
the artifacts it's very well
understandable but it's not perfect
so have fun listening the obvious
question is what is the difference
between small into big terrific drink I
think the the main difference between
the small factory in the big perfection
I think it's it's it's difficult to to
formalize or it's difficult to to just
say one one sentence about was the
difference in my experience in the past
project I was involved in we observed
just some situations where we need to to
do maybe even a small refactoring but
that involves a lot of parts in the
system and that maybe goes really into
the kernel of the system and we need we
cannot fit what we were not able to
finish this factoring in an hour on a
day we just need some weeks a month to
to really complete this refactoring and
I would say this this was a large
refactoring or a big refactoring but I
cannot say okay if you have more than
five classes involved it's a big
factoring or not
and maybe it just depends on how much
time do you need to implement the
factoring and how many pieces of your
system are affected by that that
refactoring I think that's that's the
main difference and there's a lot of
additional questions coming up if you if
you think about larger infections
because if you do refactoring for for
several weeks or several month maybe
even there are a lot of questions coming
up like how do you integrate small steps
and do are you doing the reflector in
small steps or are you doing the
factoring in herre
well and branches and stuff like that so
a lot of interesting questions coming up
with these kind of factories and they
are typically more more complicated to
to do than these kind of smaller
factions which which each each developer
can just do it with the IDE during the
normal development okay so um basically
what you're saying is the difference is
in the time that it takes to actually do
the refactoring so what is it that that
actually make those refactorings appear
because especially if you do refactoring
all the time anyway you shouldn't have
such gigantic problems in your code that
make you yeah well refactor the code for
such a long period of time I think you
can you can even try to avoid the
affections by doing small factions all
the time and you should you really
should do this doing all the small
reflections all the time
but I think and and that it's my
experience that you can come into some
situations um where you have you have a
factory system all the time but we
observed oh III have misunderstood some
domain concept significantly or I I
forgot to to think about a specific
domain concept in the beginning or maybe
did you just learn learn more stuff over
time and and if this if you are learning
or if this additional knowledge that you
gained over time and maybe effect a
central part of your system it might be
necessary to to change the central part
of his system and if you have a lot of
dependencies on the central part of your
system and it might not be even so so so
easy to just say okay I renamed this
class once it's just a simple factoring
it's easy to do in five minutes but if
you need to change for example maybe an
inherit
since hierarchy in the central part of
your system because you've learned that
this inherits hike is just just bad or
just not the right structure and you
have learned it after you you you built
huge part of the system because you have
now a different point of view or new
aspects coming into the system
you can just find yourself in this
situation we need we need adapt a lot of
parts in the system and I think you will
not be able to do it in a day or in two
days and then you're you're in this
situation maybe it's it's not so often
if you do this small fractions all the
time and you can avoid large
refactorings and mostly by doing all
this more effectively all the time but I
think you cannot really be sure that you
will never get into the situation of
having such a problem where you need a
lot of refactoring okay so um how do I
actually do that I mean changing a
central part of the system because do I
just say okay so I'm gonna stop for the
next month clean this mess up and then
I'm going to continue the real
development of additional functionality
yeah that's one one that's really one
approach are you doing doing larger
factories just stop the normal
development to refactoring and then
continue with a normal normal
development of your system but it's um
it's difficult if you have a large team
and you have a lot of stuff to implement
so you cannot say to 20 people we
stopped because maybe it's not possible
to refactor the central part with
training people in parallel so maybe
maybe two or three people can can do the
real refactoring and true can implement
the real refactoring and what should the
others the other 17 people do should do
in that piece of time they can do
holidays or whatever but maybe it's it's
not possible in some situations and in
the typical agile development methods or
development ways of programming the idea
is to do even the larger refactoring
step by step doing
a lot of small refactorings but that
needs just a digital force about this
refrigerant had to split up a large
refactoring to small factorings is not
perform any of these larger affections
it's not obvious how to to split it into
it's not trivial I'll just split them
into small effect and small steps and in
some situations you can cannot even
think about what should I do after I've
implemented these five steps what what
is the sixth or seventh step and for the
refactorings it's really complicated to
foresee all these small steps for a
large refactoring and if you're in such
a situation you can just start with you
with the first steps and with
first-first towards and moving forward
somehow and then it's it's interesting
when you integrate your changes into the
year the common code repository because
if you commit your changes back into the
code repository and typically and in
many agile development methods you do it
all the time
after each hour or minute even those
changes become visible to the rest of
the team and then you need to
communicate somehow inside the team why
do you change what piece of code what is
the refactoring about where does
refactoring moves moves to and was a
target of refactoring was the tire
design so that all the team members are
aware of these refactoring so that they
know why isn't this method advocated and
why are these parts of the system
changed because they are changed with
small factories maybe but maybe the the
overall design is not getting better
because you maybe first need to move
some step forward and then you can
really finish the larger factory or
finish a part of this larger factoring
with improving the design so it simply
if you a simple very very simple example
for this is if you rename a method
without refactoring tool so typically
first you you add an
additional method with a new name and
then you forward from the old method to
the new method and then we remove the
old method and if you commit all these
different steps back into the version
control you and in the middle of the
refactoring the design is it's worse
than before because you have two methods
with the same behavior and different
names and nobody knows why are two
different methods with different names
and stuff like that so it's it's really
good voice in the middle of the
refactoring before it gets better
and so it's really on this simple small
example it doesn't matter because you
can you can fix it in the next hour and
that's it and nobody will notice you but
if you do a large refactoring those
changes gets visible to the team and
people get gets nervous and and and
somehow they don't know what what to do
with these with these intermediate
design steps so it's really important I
think to communicate the refactoring
inside the team and to together an
overall impression what the refactoring
is about okay so but but it's not
recommended to come up with a complete
strategy for doing the whole refactoring
instead hear you say that you just do
for a few steps and then you plan the
next few steps and go step by step more
or less I think it's a it's a good idea
to have an overall idea of what the the
main steps are to accomplish the
refactoring or to to to to improve the
design and in the and the way you would
like to get it improve but the real fine
real small steps while doing the
refactoring I think it's not possible to
foresee them all up front so you even if
you even if you if you think you can you
can't foresee them I'm pretty sure that
you will learn while doing the
refactoring that some of these steps are
just stupid or that they need to be
executed in a different order and stuff
like that so you need to adapt and
change your your let's say you were
factoring
or your vectoring idea all the time
while doing perfection and it's not bad
it's good because you learn about the
refactoring and you learn how to more
efficiently do the refactoring and what
difficulties may occur and asserts it's
basically much like a big design up
front so you are not doing a big design
of the refactoring itself up front but
instead you just say okay I'm going to
do it the edgehog way and and learn
while while I go yeah I think so okay so
how do I do that with my versioning
system I mean should I do
a branch what do I do if I have a
versioning system that uses pessimistic
locking where I have to check out each
file that I'm going to change and if
this this refactoring is is affecting
almost in everything in the versioning
system that might be a big nightmare to
check out everything so so what do i do
how do how do I deal with that I think
at one point is um why should why should
I check in some changed into the version
control for for refactoring because I do
maybe continuous integration yeah so I
would like to I would like that the
other team members are benefiting from
from the changes all the time that I
adapt that code to the new changes and
stuff like that and if you if you do
such a large refactoring in parallel to
the normal development on the main main
code stream of the version control it's
it's quite difficult to to step back
into the from the refactoring it's quite
difficult if you're saying okay I will
do these small steps to the larger
Factory and do some more steps and some
more steps and some other people are
checking in some new features and stuff
like that it's all all intertwined
somehow and if you then find yourself in
a situation where you think oh mmm that
was the wrong direction for the for the
large refactoring and that that happens
in the real world
and then you really would like to step
back just to to reverse your changes for
the reflection but only those changes
are affecting of course not the changes
that the other team members I have
integrated to the version control and
that's that gets really difficult if you
have just if you are all working with
the refactoring and the normal
development on the same stream and for
such situations I think it's beneficial
to work on a branch while doing the the
larger refactoring but if I say working
on a branch for latter infection I do
not mean to work for the next two or
three months on the branch and then
after you've completed the complete we
have a whole refactoring then merge it
back into the head I think of going in
in small branch steps think like that so
doing some small steps in the branch and
then merge the branch back into the head
if you if you're sure that those changes
are are good and beneficial for the
system and then moving on again in the
branch with the refactoring doing some
small steps with refactoring the branch
and then merge the branch back that you
emerged the Brauns back into the main
stream and into the head frequently so
because it's it's really it's it's a
nightmare if you if you have a bunch for
three month or whatever may be changing
your central inheritance hierarchy or
whatever in the system and you need to
merge it back after three month and two
into the head it's just it's a real
nightmare cannot you cannot really do it
so basically I would just plan some
steps ahead yeah then I do a branch yeah
then I work on those steps and if some
of the steps are rather not such good
ideas and I'll just go back those steps
and yeah then I have some some defined
state and then I merge the branch back
into the main line and yeah I continued
with this branch for the next few steps
of my refactoring yeah we call we call
those points often they're safe points
kind of a safe point where you merge it
back and you give me someone safe that
it's a good state of the
your affection to murdered back in today
and into the head and your at this kind
of safe point and then you move on okay
so it's there any kind of sort of
literature or or established patterns
about that I think that there are no
established patterns about larger
refactorings or about bigger refactoring
problems a colleague of mine Stefan oak
he wrote a book about refactorings and
together with me and and we try to
collect some some typical problems some
typical patterns and typical behaviors
in agile teams and how you can deal with
these kind of legs let's say the safe
points of branches and and other team
techniques mostly team techniques less
technical techniques more team
techniques how to deal in an agile team
with these kind of at refactorings it's
called large refactorings restructuring
comp doing complex restructuring
successfully or somehow like that and
more familiar with the german title not
with the english one but there is an
English version of the book out and it's
published by Wiley so I think you can
you will find it if you take a look for
if you search for refactoring and but I
don't know I don't know any other
literature of papers about large
refactoring so I think that there are
other difficult we're factoring
situations where nice books are out for
example if you take a look at what
happens if you have a database
connection or if you're a fan object
relational mapping in your system and
you would like to refactor for example
your database structure or if you would
like to refactor your domain model and
that needs to - or that results in
modifying somehow the object relational
mapping and how we can do refactoring
small set of that and they're very nice
book out it's written by Scott Ambler
and and and a colleague of
colleague of him I forgot the name
Android database techniques I think it's
somehow called a base refactorings or
it's it's it's published only in the
Signature Series
but isn't Wesley in the Martin Fowler
Signature Series so what I actually do
with databases I mean obviously the
problem is that I have this database in
production and there is a lot of data in
there and as soon as I changed the
schema
I have this problem that I have existing
data that I somehow have to change and
in migrate so what I do about that
and interestingly even if it's a if it's
a completely different approach there is
nothing to do with objects or with
inheritance or whatever you can find
pretty similar patterns that you can
apply for for object relational mapping
or relational schemas on the database
and how to refactor them for example if
you have if you have if you would like
to split if you would like to split some
some some definitions some some
attribute in your class and indeed to
adapt to change your schema you can even
adapt your schema step by step by for
example like these rename method
refactoring add an additional column and
somehow deprecated an old column somehow
even if it's not available in database
systems it's kind of marking something
as deprecated but you can mark it some
somewhere else as deprecated that
everybody knows oh this this kind of
deprecated and you can migrate the data
to the new schema version a step by step
and then maybe some some point in time
remove the old column for example so
there a lot of similar techniques that
you can apply to object relational
mapping and then relational schemes for
the database isn't there another problem
also on the like cultural level because
databases I often get here this this
notion that the database is is surviving
applications and there are more the the
the database has a longer life span then
application it's and it's there for
mothers carved in stone
while the the while the application is
really soft and unchangeable it was in
is there a problem talking a DBA intro
changing the ski mattress because it's
not really convenient anymore
I think it depends on the people working
with a database and on the the let's say
administrators or it was really really
working with the database and there
there many people out there were really
convinced that developing software and
agile ways is a good it's a good idea
and it's a good way of developing
software and they're really happy with
them having changing the schema all the
time and in the current and the project
where I'm currently involved in we we
are changing the schema while we are
developing so not not the production
schema but the schema in development
let's say every two or three days adding
stuff and removing staff renaming tables
or whatever so it's a real it's a really
maybe a to agile way of dealing with it
with the database but it's really it
works quite easily with scripts where
you just put the changes of the schema
into intern sequel script and that's it
and then if you if we publish a release
we just collect all these theses let's
say Delta scripts we send it to the to
the administrator of the database and
say ok we will test it in an integration
environment and we put it into
production for the release anthem that's
it he's happy with it maybe he's not
happy if you need to do this every five
days working on the production data but
in in our release cycles it's it's
easily manageable so and those scripts
also migrate the the data in the
production yes yes we we have scripts
that migrate did the real schema
definition and it didn't escape that
migrate the data and that's that's one
situation you can think of other
situations where these data migrations
not so easily possible on this equal
level we need some some more logic and
you can even implement some some more
batch programs or whatever that migrate
the data or you can think of lazy lazy
migration strategies where you implement
to your software strategies where the
object relational mapping for example is
able to to load the data out of the old
schema as well as from the new schema
and if it's loaded once from the old
schema and put into this new schema it's
inside the new schema and it's from from
there on load from the new new schema
from a new version and no longer from
the old version so you have this kind of
lazy migration techniques built into the
software but it makes her software more
complicated because you need to have
these kind of at least the loading
techniques in the loading mechanisms for
many different versions it becomes more
complicated if you have what is three or
four different schema versions we have
all the loading techniques and you need
to migrate the data from schema to
schema lazily it's quite complicated but
it might be necessary if you have real a
huge database which you cannot just say
ok I migrated my terabytes of data just
in five minutes or whatever so but but
you are using scripts instead of this
lazy approach yeah we are ok because we
have a database with some bites
but that's heads
it's Hannibal Hannibal for for database
ok so um and I mean another like like
point of stability usually is if you
have a published API or you have some
web services that you offer to people
that you might even not be aware of who
the extra clients are so what do you do
with that that's that's really difficult
I think if you have a published API in
contrast to adjust public API if you
have real published API we do not know
your clients so for example typical if
you're implementing frameworks or
platforms like for example the Eclipse
team does with the rich client platform
or this
bring framework implementing stuff or
whatever even if you have a small open
source project we have published API you
really really some sometimes you really
would like to change this API but you
know if you change this API you will
break your clients and most of the
changes you can think of foreign foreign
published API are breaking clients so
it's really really complicated to change
these api's and it makes you think about
refactoring the API twice because you
some I think should I really do this
refactoring on the API or should or not
and if you have a let's say a
compatibility
I'm idea in your mind that you would
like to have you published API be
compatible in upwards and downwards
compatible in the future you just cannot
change it at all in the future and you
need to find some some strategies how to
deal with those those situations
typically for example the JDK or many
libraries they are doing some kind of
deprecation they deprecated methods or
classes or whatever parts of the
published API and the providing new API
for people to adapt and they hope that
all the clients will adapt to this new
API version in the future that they can
skip in some point in the future the the
old deprecated API is it's didn't happen
for the JDK yeah you don't there's just
so many kinds and they do not want to
break break the clients and the eclipse
project they they have a similar problem
because they have a huge set of
published api's and they they ensure a
binary compatibility all the time for
every version and it's it's really
complicated to to improve those api's
over time there exist some techniques
and some some some nice nice ideas how
we can can change published API is in a
compatible way like having an interface
and a published API is a typical pattern
and having an abstract implementation
with an interface in the published API
as well so that clients can implement or
can extend the abstract implementation
instead of the interface and you are
able to add for example methods to the
interface without breaking your clients
because you can add the default
implementation to the abstract class and
the client is sauce and binary
compatible with it it's a one pattern
just one pattern there exist some some
more patterns adapter mechanisms adding
interfaces instead of changing
interfaces stuff like that but it's it's
real it's a big problem because if you
if you promise backwards compatibility
you're always stuck with is ever-growing
system syndrome you know I think ok I
need to be backward compatible all the
time and I want to change and I'm going
to improve my API but I need to add API
instead of changing it or instead of
just making it better so we add API and
you add API and system gets bigger and
bigger over time it gets more ugly and
maybe I think it's better and at some
point of time to just make a cut and
change the API in in a breakable way or
that you're breaking your clients and it
depends need to adapt to this ok so
basically the problem is that you get
more and more increased complexity and
and it's yet time you need to say ok I'm
going to cut that off the answer yeah
they're interesting techniques coming up
and to inside the Eclipse project into
inside the Eclipse IDE where you can
script your refactorings so if you feel
build a library and you build a
framework or whatever with the published
API and you for example or you rename a
method in inside the public API and you
can script that refactoring and you can
publish the script the refactoring
script together with your new version of
the API so that the client is not binary
or source compatible
but the client can apply that script
automatically on the code so it it seems
for the kind it seems like you're
actually doing the refactoring of the
published API right now in the IDE so
the references to that changed method
are adapted automatically and that's a
nice nice way of helping the clients to
adapt to new versions of the API if you
change the API in a breakable way okay
and in that relies on the Java
refactorings that are built into HR ID
yeah you can I'm not sure I think you
cannot you cannot write you those
scripts manually they just recorded
while you do executing the automatic
refactorings of the Eclipse IDE and I
think they're all scriptable with the
actual miles with current milestones of
3.3 so it's not really completely
implemented for three - I think with the
milestone - or with my some one or two
it's completed so hey is that going
to solve my problems if I have for
example is the file and some some kind
of web servers or cross-platform stuff
no I don't think so
so you have a cross cross platform stuff
or if you have a web service or stuff
like that it's it's you have the same
problems okay so thanks Martine for for
talking about large refactorings
anything else you want to add no nothing
specific it was a pleasure of being on
this show so thank you very much yeah
thank you
and thanks for listening of course so
hope you enjoy the next episodes as well
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license
see the software engineering radio
website for details
[Music]
you